<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="RNG_A-Painful-Case.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="RNG_A-Painful-Case.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<!-- DTD interne pour le tiret cadratin -->
<!DOCTYPE text [
   <!ENTITY mdash "—">
]>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Painful Case</title>
                <author ref="https://data.bnf.fr/fr/11909158/james_joyce/">
                    <forename>James</forename>
                    <surname>Joyce</surname>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Édition réalisée pour l'évaluation du module de XML-TEI du Master TNAH de
                    l'École nationale des chartes</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encodage par</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Sarah</forename>
                        <surname>Bénière</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>École nationale des chartes</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                <date when="2023-02">Février 2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author ref="https://data.bnf.fr/fr/11909158/james_joyce/">
                            <forename>James</forename>
                            <surname>Joyce</surname>
                        </author>
                        <title>Dubliners</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <date when-iso="2008">2008</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="JamesDuffy">
                        <persName>James Duffy</persName>
                        <note>Personnage principal</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="EmilySinico">
                        <persName>Emily Sinico</persName>
                        <note> Épouse du <persName ref="#CapitaineSinico">Capitaine
                                Sinico</persName>, mère de <persName ref="#MarySinico">Mary
                                Sinico</persName>, a entretenu une relation avec <persName
                                ref="#JamesDuffy">James Duffy</persName>. </note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="CapitaineSinico">
                        <persName>Captain Sinico</persName>
                        <note>Mari de <persName ref="#EmilySinico">Emily Sinico</persName> et père
                            de <persName ref="#MarySinico">Mary Sinico</persName>
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="MarySinico">
                        <persName>Mary Sinico</persName>
                        <note>Fille de <persName ref="#EmilySinico">Emily Sinico</persName> et du
                                <persName ref="#CapitaineSinico">Capitaine Sinico</persName>.
                        </note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire1">
                        <persName>The girl</persName>
                        <note>Serveuse dans le restaurant de George's Street</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire2">
                        <persName>James Lennon</persName>
                        <note>Conducteur du train de Sydney Parade</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire3">
                        <persName>P. Dunne</persName>
                        <note>Porteur de chemin de fer</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire4">
                        <persName>A juror</persName>
                        <note>Un juré (anonyme)</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire5">
                        <persName>Witness</persName>
                        <note>Un témoin (anonyme)</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire6">
                        <persName>Sergeant Croly</persName>
                        <note>Sergent de police</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire7">
                        <persName>Constable57E</persName>
                        <note>Agent de police</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire8">
                        <persName>Dr Halpin</persName>
                        <note>Chirurgien au City of Dublin Hospital </note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire9">
                        <persName>Mr H. B. Patterson Finlay</persName>
                        <name>Représentant de la compagnie ferroviaire</name>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire10">
                        <persName>The jury</persName>
                        <note>Groupe des jurés (anonyme)</note>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Secondaire11">
                        <persName>The Deputy Coroner</persName>
                        <note>Médecin légiste</note>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>
            <head type="nouvelle" rend="alignement(centré) casse(majuscules)">A PAINFUL CASE</head>

            <div type="histoire">
                <p> 
                    Mr James Duffy lived in Chapelizod because he wished to live as far as possible
                    from the city of which he was a citizen and because he found all the other
                    suburbs of Dublin mean, modern and pretentious. He lived in an old sombre house
                    and from his window he could look into the disused distillery or upwards along
                    the shallow river on which Dublin is built. The lofty walls of his uncarpeted
                    room were free from pictures. He had himself bought every article of furniture
                    in the room: a black iron bedstead, an iron washstand, four cane chairs, a
                    clothes-rack, a coal-stuttle, a fender and irons and a square table on which lay
                    a double desk. A bookcase had been made in an alcove by means of shelves of
                    white wood. The bed was clothed with white bed-clothes and a black and scarlet
                    rug covered the foot. A little hand-mirror hung above the washstand and during
                    the day a white-shaded lamp stood as the sole ornament of the mantelpiece. The
                    books on the white wooden shelves were arranged from below upwards according to
                    bulk. A complete Wordsworth stood at one end of the lowest sheld and a copy of
                    the <emph rend="italic">Maynooth Catechism</emph>, sewn into the cloth cover of
                    a notebook, stood at one end of the top shelf. Writing materials were always on
                    the desk. In the desk lay a manuscript translation of Hauptmann's
                    <emph rend="italic">Michael Kramer</emph>, the stage directions of which were
                    written in purple ink, and a little sheaf of papers held together by a brass
                    pin. In these sheets a sentence was inscribed from time to time and, in an
                    ironical moment, the headline of an advertisement for <emph rend="italic">Bile
                        Beans</emph> had been pasted on to the first sheet. On lifting the lid of
                    the desk a faint fragrance escaped&mdash;the fragrance of new cedarwood pencils
                    or of a bottle of gum or of an over-ripe apple which might have been left there
                    and forgotten. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    Mr Duffy abhorred anything which betokened physical or mental disorder. A
                    medieval doctor would have called him saturnine. His face, which carried the
                    entire tale of his years, was of the brown tint of Dublin streets. On his long
                    and rather large head grew dry black hair and a tawny moustache did not quite
                    cover an unamiable mouth. His cheekbones also gave his face a harsh character;
                    but there was no harshness in the eyes which, looking at the world from under
                    their tawny eyebrows, gave the impression of a man ever alert to greet a
                    redeeming instinct in others but often disappointed. He lived at a little
                    distance from his body, regarding his own acts with doubtful side-glances. He
                    had an odd autobiographical habit which led him to compose in his mind from time
                    to time a short sentence about himself containing a subject in the third person
                    and a predicate in the past tense. He never gave alms to beggars and walked
                    firmly, carrying a stout hazel. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    He had been for many years cashier of a private bank in Baggot Street. Every
                    morning he came in from Chapelizod by tram. At midday he went to Dan Burke's and
                    took his lunch&mdash;a bottle of lager beer and a small trayful or arrowroot
                    biscuits. At four o'clock he was set free. He dined in an eating-house in
                    George's Street where he felt himself safe from the society of Dublin's gilded
                    youth and where there was a certain plain honesty in the bill of fare. His
                    evenings were spent either before his landlady's piano or roaming about the
                    outskirts of the city. His liking for Mozart's music brought him sometimes to an
                    opera or a concert: these were the only dissipations of his life.
                </p>
                <p> 
                    He had neither companions nor friends, church nor creed. He lived his spiritual
                    life without any communion with others, visiting his relatives at Christmas and
                    escorting them to the cemetery, when they died. He performed these two social
                    duties for old dignity's sake but conceded nothing further to the conventions
                    which regulate the civic life. He allowed himself to think that in certain
                    circumstances he would rob his bank but, as these circumstances never arose, his
                    life rolled out evenly&mdash;an adventureless tale. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    One evening he found himself sitting beside two ladies in the Rotunda. The
                    house, thinly peopled and silent, gave distressing prophecy of failure. 
                    <seg type="discours-direct">
                        <seg type="discours-citant" subtype="incise-position-initiale">
                            <persName ref="#EmilySinico">The lady who sat next him</persName>
                            looked round at the deserted house once or twice and then
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">said</w>
                            <pc function="introducteur-discours-rapporté">:</pc>
                        </seg>
                        <lb/>
                        <seg type="discours-cité">
                            <q type="spoken">
                                <pc function="introducteur-dicours-rapporté">&mdash;</pc>
                                What a pity there is such a poor house to-night! It's so hard on people to have
                                to sing to empty benches.
                            </q>
                        </seg>
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    He took the remark as an invitation to talk. He was surprised that she seemed so
                    little awkward. While they talked he tried to fix her permanently in his memory.
                    When he learned that the young girl beside her was her daughter he judged her to
                    be a year or so younger than himself. Her face, which must have been handsome,
                    had remained intelligent. It was an oval face with strongly marked features. The
                    eyes were very dark blue and steady. Their gaze began with a defiant note but
                    cwas confused by what seemed a deliberate swoon of the pupil into the iris,
                    revealing for an instant a temperament of great sensibility The pupil reasserted
                    itself quickly, this halk-diclosed nature fell again under the reign of
                    prudence, and her astrakhan jacket, moulding a bosom of a certain fulness,
                    struck the note of defiance more definitely.
                </p>
                <p> 
                    He met her again a few weeks afterwards at a concert in Earlsfort Terrace and
                    seized the moments when her daughter's attention was diverted to become
                    intimate. 
                    <seg type="discours-narrativisé">
                        <persName ref="#Emily-Sinico">She</persName>
                        <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">alluded</w> once or twice to 
                        <persName ref="#CapitaineSinico">her husband</persName>
                    </seg> 
                    but her tone was not such as to make the allusion a warning. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="pragmatique">
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">Her</w>
                        name was Mrs Sinico.
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">Her</w>
                        husband's great-great-grandfather had come from Leghorn. 
                        <phr type="nominal" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">Her husband</phr>
                        was captain of a mercantile boat plying between Dublin and Holland; and 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">they</w> 
                        had one child.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p> 
                    Meeting her a third time by accident he found courage to make an appointment.
                    She came. This was the first of many meetings; they met always in the evening
                    and chose the most quiet quarters for their walks together. Mr Duffy, however,
                    had a distaste for underhand ways and, finding that they were compelled to meet
                    stealthily, he forced her to ask him to her house. Captain Sinico encouraged his
                    visits, thinking that his daughter's hand was in question. He had dismissed his
                    wife so sincerely from his gallery of pleasures that he did not suspect that
                    anyone else would take an interest in her. As the husband was often away and the
                    daughter out giving music lessons Mr Duffy had many opportunities of enjoying
                    the lady's society. Neither he nor she had any such adventure before and neither
                    was conscious of any incongruity. Little by little he entangled his thoughts
                    with hers. He lent her books, provided her with ideas, shared his intellecutal
                    life with her. She listened to all. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    Sometimes in return for his theories she gave out some fact of her own life.
                    With almost maternal solicitude 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale" function="introducteur-discours-rapporté">
                            <persName ref="#EmilySinico">she</persName> urged him
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="infinitive">
                            <w type="particule" function="conjonction-subordination">to</w> 
                            let his nature open to the full
                        </cl>
                    </seg>; she became his confessor. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#JamesDuffy">He</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">told</w> her
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            for some time he had assisted at the meetings of an Irish Socialist Party 
                            where he had felt himself a unique figure amidst a score of sober workmen 
                            in a garret lit by an inefficient oil-lamp.
                        </cl>
                    </seg> 
                    When the party had divided into three sections, each under its own leader and 
                    in its own garret, he had discontinued his attendances. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="semi-libre"> The workmen's discussions, 
                        <cl type="incise" subtype="position-médiane">he said</cl>,
                        were too timorous; the interest they took in the question of wages was inordinate.
                    </seg> 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">He felt</cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            they were hard-featured realists
                        </cl>
                        <w type="conjonction" subtype="coordination">and</w>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            they resented an exactitude which was the product of a leisure not within their reach.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="semi-libre">No social revolution, 
                        <cl type="incise" subtype="position-médiane">he told her</cl>, 
                        would be likely to strike Dublin for some centuries.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="hybride">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#EmilySinico">She</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">asked</w> him
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="interrogative-directe">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">why</w> 
                            did he not write out his thoughts.
                        </cl> 
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="locutoire-avec-incise">
                        For what,
                            <cl type="incise" subtype="position-finale">
                                he asked her, with careful scorn.                            
                            </cl>
                        To compete with phasemongers, incapable of thinking consecutively for sixty seconds? To submit 
                        <w type="pronom" subtype="réflexif" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">himself</w> 
                        to the criticisms of an obtuse middle class which entrusted
                        its morality to policemen and its fine arts to impresarios?
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p> 
                    He went often to her little cottage outside Dublin; often they spent their
                    evenings alone. Little by little, as their thoughts entangled, 
                    <seg type="discours-narrativisé">
                        they spoke of subjects less remote.
                    </seg>
                    Her companionship was like a warm soil about an exotic. Many times she allowed the
                    dark to fall upon them, refraining from lighting the lamp. The dark discreet
                    room, their isolation, the music that still vibrated in their ears united them.
                    This union exalted him, wore away the rough edges of his character,
                    emotionalized his mental life. Sometimes he caught himself listening to the
                    sound of his own voice. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">                            
                            <persName ref="#JamesDuffy">He</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="pensée">thought</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            in her eyes he would ascend to an angelical stature;
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    and, as he attached the fervent nature of his companion more and more closely to him, 
                    <seg type="segment-contextualisant" function="introducteur-discours-indirect-libre">
                        he heard the strange impersonal voice which he recognized as his own,
                    </seg> 
                    insisting on the soul's incurable loneliness. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="endophasique">
                        We cannot give ourselves, 
                        <phr type="verbal" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">it said</phr>: 
                        we are our own.
                    </seg> 
                    The end of these discourses was that one night during which she
                    had shown every sign of unusual excitement, Mrs Sinico caught up his hand
                    passionately and pressed it to her cheek. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    Mr Duffy was very much surprised. Her interpretation of his words disillusioned
                    him. He did not visit her for a week; then 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <persName ref="#JamesDuffy">he</persName>
                        <w type="verbe" subtype="action">wrote</w> to her 
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="gérondive">
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole" function="conjonction-subordination">asking</w> 
                            her to meet him.
                        </cl>
                    </seg> 
                    As he did not wish their last interview to be troubled by
                    the influence of their ruined confessional they met in a little cakeshop near
                    the Parkgate. It was cold autumn weather but in spite of the cold they wandered
                    up and down the roads of the Park for nearl three hours. 
                    <seg type="discours-direct">
                        <cl type="segment-contextualisant" function="introducteur-discours-direct">
                            They agreed to break off their intercourse</cl>
                        <pc function="introducteur-discours-direct">:</pc>
                        <q type="spoken">every bond, 
                            <cl type="incise" subtype="position-médiane">he said</cl>, 
                            is a bond to sorrow.
                        </q>
                    </seg> 
                    When they came out of the park they walked in silence towards the tram; 
                    but here she began to tremble so violently that, feeling another collapse on her part, 
                    he bade her good-bye quickly and left her. A few days later he received a parcel 
                    containing his books and music. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    Four years passed. Mr Duffy returned to his even way of life. His room still
                    bore witness of the orderliness of his mind. Some new pieces of music encumbered
                    the music-stand in the lower room and on his shelves stood two volumes by
                    Nietzsche: <emph rend="italic">Thus Spake Zarathustra</emph> and <emph
                        rend="italic">The Gay Science</emph>. He wrote seldom in the sheaf of papers
                    which lay in his desk.
                    <seg type="effet-de-discours-rapporté">
                        One of his sentences, written two months after his last interview with Mrs Sinico,
                        read: Love between man and man is impossible because there must not be
                        sexual intercourse and friendship between man and woman is impossible
                        because there must be sexual intercourse.
                    </seg> 
                    He kept away from concerts lest she should meet her. His father died; the junior partner of the bank
                    retired. And still every morning he went into the city by tram and every evening
                    walked home from the city after having dined moderately in George's Street and
                    read the evening paper for dessert. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    One evening as he was about to put a morsel of corned beef and cabbage into his
                    mouth his hand stopped. His eyes fixed themselves on a paragraph in the evening
                    paper which he had propped against the water-carafe. He replaced the morsel of
                    food on his plate and read the paragraph attenively. Then he drank a glass of
                    water, pushed his plate to one side, doubled the paper down before him between
                    his elbows and read the paragraph over and over again. The cabbage began to
                    deposit a cold white grease on his plate. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="hybride">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#Secondaire1">The girl</persName> came over to him to 
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">ask</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="interrogative-directe">
                            was his dinner not properly cooked.
                        </cl>
                    </seg> 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#JamesDuffy">He</persName> said
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            it was very good
                        </cl>
                    </seg> 
                    and ate a few mouthfuls of it with difficulty. Then he paid his bill and went out. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    He walked along quickly through the November twilight, his stout hazel stick
                    striking the ground regularly, the fringe of the buff <emph rend="italic"
                        >Mail</emph> peeping out of a side-pocket of his tight reefer overcoat. On
                    the lonely road which leads from the Parkgate to Chapelizod he slackened his
                    pace. His stick struck the ground less emphatically and his beath, issuing
                    irregularly, almost with a sighing sound, condensed in the wintry air. When he
                    reached his house he went up at once to his bedroom and, taking the paper from
                    his pocket, read the paragraph again by the failing light of the window. He read
                    it not aloud, but moving his lips as a priest does when he reads the prayers
                        <emph rend="italic">Secreto</emph>. This was the paragraph: 
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article-journal">
                <head type="article-journal" subtype="titre-principal" rend="alignement(centré) casse(majuscules)">
                    DEATH OF A LADY AT SYDNEY PARADE
                </head>
                <head type="article-journal" subtype="sous-titre" rend="alignement(centré) casse(petites-majuscules)">
                    A PAINFUL CASE
                </head>
                <p> 
                    To-day at the City of Dublin Hospital the Deputy Coroner (in the absence of Mr
                    Leverett) held an inquest on the body of Mrs Emily Sinico, aged forty-three
                    years, who was killed at Sydney Parade Station yesterday evening. The evidence
                    showed that the deceased lady, while attempting to cross the line, was knocked
                    down by the engine of the ten o'clock slow train from Kingstown, thereby
                    sustaining injuries of the head and right side which led to her death.*
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#Secondaire2">James Lennon, driver of the engine</persName>,
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">stated</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            he had been in the employment of the railway company for fifteen years.
                        </cl>
                    </seg> 
                    On hearing the guard's whistle he set the train in motion and a second or two 
                    afterwards brought it to rest in response to loud cries. The train was going slowly. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#Secondaire3">P. Dunne, railway porter</persName>,
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">stated</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            as the train was about to start he observed a woman attempting to cross the lines.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-narrativisé">
                        <persName ref="#Secondaire3">He</persName> 
                        ran towards her and shouted
                    </seg> 
                    but, before he could reach her, she was caught by the buffer of the engine and fell to the ground. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-direct" subtype="sans-incise">
                        <persName ref="#Secondaire4">A juror</persName>
                        <pc function="introducteur-discours-direct">&mdash;</pc>
                        <q type="spoken">You saw the lady fall?</q>
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-direct" subtype="sans-incise">
                        <persName ref="Secondaire5">Witness</persName>
                        <pc function="introducteur-discours-direct">&mdash;</pc>
                        <q type="spoken">Yes.</q>
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#Secondaire6">Police Sergeant Croly</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">deposed</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            when he arrived he found the deceased lying on the platform apparently dead.
                        </cl>
                    </seg> 
                    He had the body taken to the waiting-room pending the arrival of the ambulance. 
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-narrativisé">
                        <persName ref="Secondaire7">Constable 57E</persName> corroborated.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="Secondaire8">
                                Dr Halpin, assistant house surgeon of the City of Dublin Hospital
                            </persName>, 
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">stated</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            the deceased had two lower ribs fractured and had sustained severe contusions
                            of the right shoulder.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="locutoire">
                        The right side of the head had been injured in the fall. The injuries were not sufficient to have
                        caused death in a normal person. Death, 
                        <phr function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">in his opinion</phr>,
                        had been probably due to shock and sudden failure of the heart's action.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="segment-contextualisant" function="introducteur-discours-indirect-libre">
                        <persName ref="#Secondaire9">Mr H. B. Patterson Finlay</persName>, 
                        on behalf of the railway company, expressed his deep regret at the accident.
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="locutoire">
                        The company had always taken every precaution to prevent people crossing the lines except by the
                        bridges, both by placing notices in every station and by the use of patent
                        spring gates at level crossings. The deceased had been in the habit of
                        crossing the lines late at night from platform to platform and, in view of
                        certain other circumstances of the case, 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w> 
                        did not think the railway officials were to blame.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="#CapitaineSinico">Captain Sinico, of Leoville, Sydney Parade, husband of the deceased</persName>,
                    also gave evidence. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#CapitaineSinico">He</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">stated</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w>
                            <persName ref="#EmilySinico">the deceased</persName> 
                            was his wife.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="locutoire">
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">He</w> 
                        was not in Dublin at the time of the accident as 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w> 
                        had arrived only that morning from Rotterdam. 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">They</w> 
                        had been married for twenty-two years and had lived happily until about two years ago when
                        <phr type="nominal" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">his wife</phr> 
                        began to be rather intemperate in 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">her</w> 
                        habits.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#MarySinico">Miss Mary Sinico</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">said</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w>
                            of late her mother had been in the habit of going out at night to buy spirits.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    <seg>
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">She</w>,
                        witness, had often tried to reason 
                        <phr type="nominal" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">her mother</phr> 
                        and had induced her to join a league.
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="locutoire">
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">She</w> 
                        was not at home until an hour after the accident.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-narrativisé">
                        <persName ref="Secondaire10">The jury</persName> 
                        returned a verdict in accordance with the medical evidence 
                        <w type="conjonction" subtype="coordination">and</w> 
                        exonerated Lennon from all blame.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="Secondaire11">The Deputy Coroner</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="parole">said</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            it was a most painful case,
                        </cl>
                        <w type="conjonction" subtype="coordination">and</w>
                        <w type="verbe" subtype="parole" function="proposition-principale">expressed</w>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            great sympathy with Captain Sinico and his daughter.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#Secondaire11">He</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="action">urged</w> 
                            on the railway company
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="infinitive">
                            <w type="particule" function="conjonction-subordination">to</w> 
                            take strong measures to prevent the possibility of similar accidents in the future.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    No blame attached to anyone. 
                </p>
            </div>

            <div type="histoire">
                <p> 
                    Mr Duffy raised his eyes from the paper and gazed out of his windown on the
                    cheerless evening landscape. The river lay quiet beside the empty distillery and
                    from time to time a light appeared in some house on the Lucan road. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="endophasique">
                        What an end
                        <pc function="marqueur-discours-direct-libre">!</pc>
                    </seg> 
                    The whole narrative of her death revolted him and it revolted him to think that he had
                    ever spoken to her of what he held sacred. The threadbare phrases, the inane
                    expressions of sympathy, the cautious words of a reporter won over to conceal
                    the details of a commonplace vulgar death attacked his stomach.
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="endophasique">
                        Not merely had she degraded herself; she had degraded 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">him</w>.
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">He</w> saw the 
                        <w type="adjectif" subtype="qualificatif" function="marqueur-subjectivité">squalid</w> tract of her vice, 
                        <w type="adjectif" subtype="qualificatif" function="marqueur-subjectivité">miserable</w>
                        and <w type="adjectif" subtype="qualificatif" function="marqueur-subjectivité">malodorous</w>. 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">His</w> soul's companion
                        <pc function="marqueur-subjectivité">!</pc>
                    </seg> 
                    He thought of the hobbling wretches whom he had seen carrying cans and bottles to be filled by the barman.
                    <seg type="discours-direct" subtype="libre">
                        Just God, what an end
                        <pc function="marqueur-subjectivité">!</pc>
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="locutoire">
                        Evidently she had been  unfit to live, without any strength of purpose, an easy prey to habits, one
                        of the wrecks on which civilisation has been reared. But that she could have sunk so low
                        <pc function="marqueur-subjectivité">!</pc> 
                        Was it possible 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w> had deceived 
                        <w type="pronom" subtype="réflexif" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">himself</w> 
                        so utterly about her
                        <pc function="marqueur-subjectivité">?</pc>
                    </seg> 
                    He remembered her outburst of that night and interpreted it in a harsher sense than he had ever
                    done. He had no difficulty now in approving of the course he had taken. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    As the light failed and his memory began to wander he thought her hand touched
                    his. The shock which had first attacked his stomach was now attacking his
                    nerves. He put on his overcoat and hat quickly and went out. The cold air met
                    him on the threshold; it crept into the sleeves of his coat. When he came to the
                    public-house at Chapelizod Bridge he went in and ordered a hot punch. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    The proprietor served him obsequiously but did not venture to talk. 
                    <seg type="discours-narrativise">
                        There were five or six working-men in the shop discussing the value of a gentleman's 
                        estate in County Kildare.
                    </seg>
                    They drank at intervals from their huge pint tumblers and smoked, spitting often on
                    the floor and sometimes dragging the sawdust over their spits with their heavy
                    boots. Mr Duffy sat on his stoll and gazed at them, without seeing or hearing
                    them. After a while they went out and he called for another punch. He sat a long
                    time over it. The shop was very quiet. The proprietor sprawled on the counter
                    reading the <emph rend="italic">Herald</emph> and yawning. Now and again a tram
                    was heard swishing along the lonely road outside. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    As he sat there, living over his life with her and evoking alternately the two
                    images in which he now conceived her, 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="classique">
                        <cl type="principale">
                            <persName ref="#JamesDuffy">he</persName>
                            <w type="verbe" subtype="pensée">realized</w>
                        </cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            she was dead
                        </cl>
                        <pc function="conjonction-coordination">,</pc>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            she had ceased to exist
                        </cl>
                        <pc function="conjonction-coordination">,</pc>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="complétive">
                            <w type="conjonction" subtype="subordination">that</w> 
                            she had become a memory.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    He began to feel ill at ease. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect" subtype="hybride">
                        <cl type="principale">He asked himself</cl>
                        <cl type="subordonnée" subtype="interrogative-directe">
                            <w type="pronom" subtype="interrogatif" function="conjonction-subordination">what</w>
                            else could he have done.
                        </cl>
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="endophasique">
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">He</w> 
                        could not have carried on a comedy of deception with her; 
                        <w type="pronom"
                            function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w> 
                        could not have lived with her openly. 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">He</w> 
                        had done what seemed to be best. How was 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w> 
                        to blame
                        <pc function="marqueur-subjectivité">?</pc> 
                        Now that she was gone 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w>
                        understood how lonely her life must have been, sitting night after night
                        alone in that room. 
                        <phr type="nominal" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">His life</phr> 
                        would be lonely too until 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w>, too, 
                        died, ceased to exist, became a memory&mdash;if anyone remembered 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">him</w>.
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p> 
                    It was after nine o'clock when he left the shop. The night was cold and gloomy.
                    He entered the park by the first gate and walked along under the gaunt trees. He
                    walked through the bleak alleys where they had walked four years before. She
                    seemed to be near him in the darkness. At momets he seemed to feel her voice
                    touch his ear, her hand touch his. He stood still to listen. 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="endophasique">
                        Why had 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w>
                        withheld life from her
                        <pc function="marqueur-subjectivité">?</pc> 
                        Why had 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w>
                        sentenced her to death
                        <pc function="marqueur-subjectivité">?</pc>
                    </seg> 
                    He felt his moral nature falling to pieces. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    When he gained the crest of the Magazine Hill he halted and looked along the
                    river towards Dublin, the lights of which burned redly and hospitably in the
                    cold night. He looked down the slope and, at the base, in the shadow of the wall
                    of the park, 
                    <seg type="segment-contextualisant" function="introducteur-discours-indirect-libre">
                        he saw some human figure lying.
                    </seg> 
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="endophasique">
                        Those
                        <w type="adjectif" subtype="qualificatif" function="marqueur-subjectivité">venal</w> and 
                        <w type="adjectif" subtype="qualificatif" function="marqueur-subjectivité">furtive</w> loves
                    </seg> 
                    filled him with despair. 
                    <seg type="segment-contextualisant" function="introducteur-discours-indirect-libre">
                        He gnawed the rectitude of his life; he felt that he had been outcast from life's feast.
                    </seg>
                    <seg type="discours-indirect-libre" subtype="endophasique">
                        One human being had seemed to love 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">him</w> and 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">he</w> 
                        had denied her life and happiness: 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre" >he</w> 
                        had sentenced her to ignominy, 
                        <phr type="nominal" function="marqueur-subjectivité">a death of shame</phr>. 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">He</w> 
                        knew that the prostrate creatures down by the wall were watching 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">him</w> and wished 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">him</w> gone.
                        No one wanted 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre">him</w>; 
                        <w type="pronom" function="marqueur-discours-indirect-libre" >he</w> 
                        was outcast from life's feast.
                    </seg> 
                    He turned his eyes to thegrey gleaming river, winding along towards Dublin. Beyond the river he saw a
                    goods train winding out of Kingsbridge Station, like a worm with a fiery head
                    winding through the darkness, obstinately and laboriously. It passed slowly out
                    of sight; but still he heard in his ears the laborious drone of the engine
                    reiterating the syllables of her name. 
                </p>
                <p> 
                    He turned back the way he had come, the rhythm of the engine pounding in his
                    ears. He began to doubt the reality of 
                    <seg type="effet-de-discours-rapporté">
                        what memory told him.
                    </seg> 
                    He halted under a tree and allowed the rhythm
                    to die away. He could not feel her near him in the darkness nor her voice touch
                    his ear. He waited for some minutes listening. He could hear nothing: the night
                    was perfectly silent. He listened again: perfectly silent. He felt that he was
                    alone. 
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
